Time to find the pattern, but it was already patented. And so now it's like there's no incentive for companies to develop it.
Because there's no patent on it.
Oh, yeah.
No valid patent anymore.
And well.
Hmm, that has money behind it.
I mean, this entire patent issue is the whole reason why we have all this lobbyism for HFOs right now. Yeah, because when it was the ozone layer issue, the Bonsai protocol, that was in 1987, 85 was the Vienna Convention and 87 the Montreal Protocol
This was 50 years after the market introduction of R12, so the patents for R12 and R22, they were long… they were long expired
Mm-hmm.
So the companies like Dupong, Honeywell, and so on, they enjoyed having HFCs because they could take out new patents covering them or protecting them for 20 years against
fake copies, and then you take the like the late 1980s, early 1990s, when all the patents for HFCs were filed
Mm-hmm.
At 20 years and then you are now like 2012, 2013 was the market introduction of HFOs
But those patents for HFOs, they have not expired yet, so that's why they are fighting so hard.
Mm-hmm. It makes sense, but…
But the problem is that the
But…
I mean, whatever CFCs and HCFCs did to the ozone layer will be gone 100 years after we stop producing those substances. Regarding HFCs and global warming
All right.
It's less than 100 years than the global warming effect from the HFCs will be gone because they all disappeared from the atmosphere. But the trifluoritic acid from the TFA, from the HFOs will last thousands of years
In our groundwater. So this is the next, I don't know, future 100 generations which will thank us for doing this.
An apostrophe, right? Exactly.
Alright, that's…
Yeah, so
It's, it's interesting how we always think with, like, more technology, we can bail ourselves out, but
I don't know, I mean, that's gonna be a difficult one.
I really enjoyed this video yesterday from this, what is, was it, a British scientist, this woman, the video editor played
Janine… yeah, Janine Venice
Yeah, that's really great, a lot of inspiration in that video. And also in your presentation afterwards. So
Thank you, Eddie.
Let's go for a joint paper on this glacier PV
Looking forward to read more
Yep.
Thank you, thank you.
Mm-hmm.
Okay, but then I think we have talked enough now. So let's start with the lecture.
Alright, so thank you. Thank you very much, Michael. Thank you, Christian, and thanks. Good morning, or good afternoon, good evening, everybody. Thank you for being here. I want to
Start by saying this is not, I'm not
An expectant lead, and I was going to do a little bit of lead and little bit of will give you an overview
And then we'll talk on the other side after the lead lecture we'll talk a little bit. We can have a little discussion and then same with the well. So we can have like 2 breaks there.
So let me in the chat I did include the Pdf of the lecture so that you have it for reference.
All right
All right, so we're going to talk about lead and well today. So again, welcome everybody
So
And start with a little video, just like a one minute video. Kind of to get an overview of what lead is and we'll talk here.
And then I'll go over their website just
So that
I can kind of walk you through an overview, and then we'll go into the lecture slides. I won't be going very detailed because again, I'm not an expert expert, but I will provide a good overview for it
Okay, so here, let's start there.
Need for leadership and regime
Is rebuilding certification program that recognizes
Sorry. Best in class building strategies and practices. This is not letting me expand it.
This is the complement our environment and enhance our communities. Places that give people better, brighter, healthier spaces to live, work, and to receive lead certification projects pursue credits that earn points
Prerequisites and credits differ for each rating system.
Teams choose the rating system that best fits their project.
After the team completes the review process, the project is awarded a certification level based on the number of points in our intent.
So, if you're serious about saving money, conserving energy, making better building material choices, and driving innovation, then LEED is the best choice for you.
Ready to learn more? Visit usgvc.org/ So that's like an overview that they have on their website. So I'll go over their website in detail and then we'll go into the lecture.
So
Lead certification… so… let me go back here for a second.
So first of all, the rating is
Kind of managed the organization that oversees is the United States. It's a USGBC, United States Green Building Council, right? They oversee LEED. And so LEED is
leadership in energy and environmental design, right? So it's a rating system that's kind of used
To kind of essentially rate buildings. And you can go for different types of certifications and at different stages. So you could, for instance, you can go like building design and construction
You can go after that. You can look at it from an interior design and construction stage, a building operations and maintenance, right? So different, different aspects from a neighbor development standpoint, from a residential standpoint
From the urban kind of cities standpoint
And essentially it's a point system. And depending on like all these good practices and like material choices, energy choices, water use, if you're using Christine is an expert at heat pumps, he can tell you more about it
If you're using a heat pump as opposed to gas, I mean, there's all these and for each practice and each each what they call like a right choice that you make, you earn points
And you have different ratings for the points that you earn. If you earn up to 49 points, you can claim that your building is LEED certified. But if you're in 50 to 59 points, then you say that
You have a silver rating, and then 60 to 79 gold, and then 80 plus you have
Platinum. Now, in terms of the versions, there's different versions of leads. You can still go after the four, but the latest version is version five that they're using
And the other thing is there are some requirements where they call it as minimum program requirements. You absolutely have to have these
And there's no
debate on that. If you don't have this, you don't get LEED certified. So there's a minimum program requirements. And then, depending on the different
So, what you are after, and how many points are you using responsible material, local, and all of that, depending on that, you earn points, and after the minimum program requirements, you fall into different tires
So that's… and here's the website. I'm going to put this in the chat so later, if you want to
check it out, and then kind of learn more about it, and actually there's one more document I'm going to put in the chat while I go back. Give me one second.
This is
The lead… let me go back to where's the chat? Sorry.
the leader referenced this document. There's another Pdf. It's an easy read when you're going on your afternoon work. It's only 375 pages. I'm just kidding. Whenever you have time, you can go back and refer to it. So that's also there
for you to…
Roughly 2 when you want to
All right. So now
Again, so there's different things that we need to look at, right? So for instance, transportation. Do you have like a socket where you can, for EV electric vehicles to charge
Is the site sustainable? You look at water efficiency, energy use, materials and resources, indoor air quality. This awareness and education element and innovation and design
So these are different
aspects that that that we can look at and try to kind of focus on so that you can earn the points that you need to
So
If you think about why, why, why should this is the big question, right? Why should we have green buildings? So it's because buildings, right? I mean, and all of us, we spend time in built environments
And but all these built environments, they contribute for about 40% of global carbon emissions. There's a lot that happens because, again, all of us at some point in the day, unless
you are out in the wild. We are all spending times in buildings, and it's important that when we are constructing it right or even planning the construction, right? So I mean, if you're proactive about it, and you think about
can use those materials locally? Can you have responsible water use? Can you have, let's say you're ordering furniture, for instance, are you ordering furniture which has does not
Off-gas, volatile organic compounds, for instance, right? And then you also think about during the operations and maintenance of the building and stuff. So it's like a holistic approach. You're considering it. And then the idea is
I know yesterday when we talked about biophilic with the Native American perspective, one of the things is when we as humans do things, can we do it in harmony with nature? Can we do it
Looking back at the intergenerational responsibility, like Janine was saying, we need to think about the 10,000th generation, right? So that… so from a building standpoint, are we making
the right choices? Are we being responsible in the decision making, right? Often the decision making on material choices on the lighting choices, all of it. Are we doing this in a more responsible manner so that we are doing
Creating less harm and harm and after we talk about lead, the next half will talk about well, because the well talks a little bit more on the health and well-being of individuals
when they're inside the building. So I think it's important, because, I mean, building is this is more like when you consider like scientific management and stuff, we are looking more from a building standpoint. Yes, there are implications for health, but well focuses a little more on the health itself
And we'll talk about that as we both
Okay, again, again, lead, so leadership and energy and environmental design. What is that essentially an American. Oh, is it comparable to the Swiss European
Miner G plus Billy, I am not sure. Sam, that's a good question. Does anybody know
I can look… I should look that up and try to answer the question for you, Sen. Sorry, my knowledge is limited to here and I don't know the European standard there
Good question. We'll find out. We'll find out. No, no, no, please don't be sorry. We are all learning from each other, so thank you.
So this is essentially like a volume you opt in, right? You opt in and then you bring in an expert and they kind of do this evaluation. And then based on that
Depending on how many points you earn, you get the certification or you have a silver, gold or platinum status. I know in the our student union, I think is gold has gold status. They've they've done a lot of things in our student union. For one, I think
All the flooring material. I think they had it was from repurposed from another building that was being torn down or something. And they put the flooring there. And all the because they have a large food court
In the student union, all the tabletops, I think, were from Cork and other material that was previously used somewhere. They got that there. And so they have a lot of good practices. Then on one side, they do some rainwater harvesting
So all of that led to them getting I think a gold status
So the version 1 was introduced in 1998, right? And then 2007, they had like a green business certification and then 2025 and 2026, we are still using the version 5. So we're currently at version 5
Using the lead certifications. So there's different emphasis, right? So one is decarbonization, reducing the carbon footprint and stuff.
Quality of life. And you're looking at it from a building standpoint, but the implications for health
ecological conservation, restoration. So they have requirements. If you have this much land, and then how the land is being used, and if it's around the building, all of it, they try to kind of consider the environment and implications for the environment
But
broad… because at the end of it, you always ask, why should I do lead? Because to implement all of to plan and kind of be responsible, I've heard the cost sometimes
Where you have all of the different pieces from your energy standpoint, from your indoor air quality standpoint, materials, all of it, it can add
It can in some instances, they say it's $40,000, $50,000, but then also when you have the expert come in and do the evaluation, you have to pay them, like, $6,000. So it's a lot of money
But oftentimes the return of investment is in the long run, because you have typically lower operating costs. And when you lead certified itself, you're following all these
principles to save you money. And overall, it can because you're being proactive and you're incorporating all of these responsible principles
your building itself, the value of the building can go up. Then from this, this is what, right? Your reduced waste to landfills, because oftentimes for lead buildings, you're using
material that was kind of repurposed when one of the buildings were torn down and stuff. So you're reducing that. I mean, because all of… are you familiar with the
Soggy lettuce report
This is just on the side, right? When you talk about emissions in the landfill, you have, let's say, tons of construction waste, right? Going to the landfill in between there, one of us in a refrigerator
We have a lattice. We put the poor lettuce also in the landfill. If we don't… if we are not composting and everything like Christian does, you put the soggy lettuce and the lettuce ends up with all these other building material
And that also contributes to the methane emissions. You can read about the Saghi latest report. It's an interesting read
Energy and water conservation again. So one example I mentioned, if you have solar panels, I know we have a library in Tulsa. Tulsa is a city one hour away from
Stillwater, where we we are based at our university is based. They have a public library that the Tulsa public, and I'm going to type it here. You can look it up
I think actually tells public library. This building is LEED certified also is a beautiful building. We visited it
And they took us on the roof of the building, and they have all these solar panels on the roof
And they had gotten some credits for using solar panels to try and power the building and
Then water conservation again, like I mentioned here at the student union, they have. They grew their own herbs. They have a restaurant, and they use rainwater harvesting. They grow a lot of some of the produce that they use
To serve food in the restaurant here on campus. But you can also be eligible for like rebates and incentives and stuff because you are following because you have LEED certification
But I think the biggest thing is because of all these good practices, you're likely to save money from the lead. So one argument is, can we just follow the principles of lead without actually seeking the certification
Yeah, absolutely. I think if you don't have the money to get satisfied, you can still follow the good principles, right? Adopt the principles, whatever you can adopt, you adopt.
All right.
There's eight main credit categories again, and we will look over those. And again, this is where I was talking about the minimum requirements. There's some things that you have to do if you don't do it, there's no lead. I mean, and then you have the others which are
you're kind of adding on, and then you're getting the points right? So again, you can have a total of 110 points, and that when you hit the 100 and the hundreds, I mean, that's what the platinum, right? You go for the highest level
And again, these are the things that on the website had shown you, you're looking at it from the building design and construction phase, the interior design and construction operations and maintenance. And there's no set way to do it
It depends on your budget, depends on your priorities, depend on what you can do, right? What you can implement. So it's it's very tailored. Each building is different when you design it, and each each if you go to different LEED certified buildings
There's another building in town here, which is run by a large energy company, and that building is certified. There's also a little there's a school
which is LEED certified, but all of how they got the certification, how they earned the points, it's very different. It's very unique to
what the priorities were, what the budget was what they could do and couldn't do, and all of it right? So if you're looking at interior design from a commercial interior standpoint. So it's looking at
interior renovation projects. You're considering like movable furnitures, fixtures, equipment that's installed in the space. So in this case, if you're going after the interior design, so then the exterior shell would not be
Included, right? That's beyond the scope of
If you're going after this
Right? So that's why I mean, understanding what you want to go after and so that and
So it's very dependent on the decisions that you make and decisions are often made based on budget
and other considerations. Also, the priorities of an organization, what they want to do
So here's the minimum program requirements, right? You have to have a permanent location on an existing land.
Right? So it needs to be permanent location. There need to be reasonable boundaries, right, in terms of the site itself.
Right? So here they say for the building and construction operations, you need a minimum of 1,000 square feet
For the interior design side, it's a minimum of 250 square feet. So, as you see, it's not a large area, but that's the requirement. If you don't have these, if you are below for the building and construction operations plus maintenance, if you're at 900, then you cannot
go after this. These are the minimum requirements that they set
Okay.
In terms of occupancy, right, so you have different
So you have the regular occupants, and this is your primary, right? Who's primarily using the space? If it's employees, if it's residents, if it's an education building, is it students, if it's health care, is it the doctors, nurses? But then you can have also
If it's doctors and nurses, because they work there, right? But if you can have in the hospital healthcare system, but you can also have patients shut them, right? You can have depending on the you can have long term and short-term visitors, right? Sometimes you have
In the healthcare system, a patient is there for like a month along with the caregiver. So you need to start thinking about that. Or are they just an outpatient clinic? They're just coming and going. And same thing with students. Is it students who are enrolled in a four-year program or is it
As students who are taking a certificate program, so it all depends. And then, let's say you have a retail store, you have employees who work in the retail store, but then you have, like, your customers, right, who visit the retail store
So, depending on how you understand occupancy and stuff. And I think they refer to this ASHRAE. I mean, Christian, you might know this better. I'm not an expert or not too much
I should, but I don't pay too much attention to 62.1.
62. Okay, okay, okay. I think that's the reference that they kind of refer to that
For the lead
There is an option, there is a provision, it doesn't mean that you have to have… the space needs to be completely completed and operational, right?
Now, here they say that if it's an incomplete space allowed if less than 40% of the gross flow area is incomplete. In other words, at least 60% needs to be completed and operational
If it's not, then you cannot go after it. And then the owner, they commit. They provide the timeline on when the other space would be completed. And so there's like an agreement and the points
You earn some of the points, and then some of the points after it's finished, then you can… but this is almost like you're being proactive because when you are
Kind of building itself. I think you want to plan this, like, way before. It's not an afterthought, right? You're being very intentional in your material choices, in where you should have
From water efficiency standpoint, energy efficiency standpoint, what lighting should you use? All of those, right? So if you're starting this early, even though you have not completed you're kind of committing to your in the process you're learning also like
And then you say, like, okay, I think based on our budget, these are all things that we can do here. And then here we are just with this, we are trying to just get certified, and then we are hoping that once we have the other parts, all of it completed
We hope to move to a gold status, a platinum status, and so on, right? But so those future states, because you'll have an audit again after everything is completed
And if you have this one part that is awesome, and then this other part that is not doing well at all, that can affect your credits. I mean, you can… you can go from being certified to not certified, right? Because after that, you look at the whole building
When once everything is completed. So it's important because you said that you would do something, but you come back and you don't do it. You can get into trouble, right?
For the Platinum requirements, again, that's like the high end, right? So your external requirements for like decarbonization.
energy efficiency for everything. This is like you're setting the bar, right? So your building is, like, the… the example that everybody else is looking to if they want to try to get certified. So for everything you're going above and beyond
The minimum requirements to try and kind of achieve this.
Okay, so now how do you go about this? So you're selecting which rating system might be most appropriate. Then you go on the website and you register. Usually, I mean, you do it with a consultant. I would do it with the consultant, right? You're having your discussions
You see that you meet the prerequisites. Are you meeting the minimum requirements, right? You have the land, permanent land, you have this much of land set aside. And those minimum requirements. And then you can start looking into the credits
And you submit the documentation, and then you have an evaluator, they would come and review and they say, okay, yeah, you have 103 points. And so you are platinum certified
Right, so it's a pretty straightforward process there
Again, in terms of what documents you would need to provide your construction documents, specification, a lot of photos, videos of and there'll be a site visit too where you have
the evaluator come and you're showing your energy and water models and stuff. I know like occupancy sensors, right? In buildings where you're saying if, okay, if and I
Oklahoma State University, I think over
Five years. They saved $10 million
By one having occupancy sensors, number two, where they sent out these mass emails right to any faculty, staff, anybody working across the campus
To be responsible with the practices. So if we have a long weekend, we ask to
shut down the computer completely, for instance. I know we are told, for instance, if I'm if I'm walking out taking a walk, if I'm not in my office for more than 22 seconds, at least that's the number they gave, why not turn off my
But if you have sensors, nowadays we have different sensors, it's easy to kind of use sensors and be more responsible, right? One of the arguments they talk about, I mean, last class we talk about how do you create
modification in behavior, right? How do paradigm search and stuff. Nowadays it's easy. I mean, you have these smart sensors. I mean, even if you're doing this to your home, right? I mean, we have a sense, it tells us like, oh
this much energy is being used. When you get feedback, right? And then you can be more responsible about it
OC also started switching off the AC at 5am, so you can… Yes, yes, Christian. And if you come in here before 8am, that's why I have my fan here in my office.
Why do you need to come with, like, ice cubes or something.
Right, right, right. Yeah, yeah, they are very, very
The funny part is I moved into a renovated building and now I can't open the windows anymore and the older buildings I used to be in, you can open the windows if the weather is cold enough outside.
Right, right, right, right, right, right. I mean, that's one thing right here, they talk about energy efficiency and they want to kind of, they call it tight, right? They want to keep everything tight, everything closed
Mm-hmm.
But on the other side, I know it's beyond the scope of this discussion perhaps, but we have what we call sick building syndrome
Right? And I
Now, the best, the best building is an insulated box without doors and windows.
Yes, yes, there is a… there is an amazing talk. I know I'm deviating a little bit, but sorry. But I think it's important, it's relevant. It's about learning at the end of the day
Let me see if I can pull it up. What was the name?
These are green,
Bacteria
buildings
Jessica Green. When we're taking a little break, we'll watch this. I think this is really, really good because what she does is she goes to building because indoor air quality is one of the factors that we should
take into consideration. So, as we are going about trying to be tight, so what she does is she goes around and takes… she does air sampling, and then she tests this, and then she creates these maps. And one of the things she says is
Christine is where you have and she did a study where you have classrooms in a building and they did it where everything is closed and you have certain bacteria in different spaces. And then when you open up the windows
Mm-hmm.
On both sides, right? And you have cross ventilation. It's almost like a flush. It kind of flushes out, and yeah, yeah, we'll watch and talk, talk. So
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Okay, sorry.
There you go.
Okay, okay. So, in terms of material declarations, we need to also consider, like, so your environmental, product declaration. That's your EPD
Right? So this is like a verified document that reports the environmental impact of a material or product over its entire lifecycle. So you have to kind of have that those documents in place kind of showing. This is why when you buy any furniture, right, I mean, you look at
And then see because indoor air quality and all of all of the things that kind of all the off gassing and everything that comes from
the space is it's really crazy in terms of when we do, we've done some indoor air quality studies, and I'll talk about that in a little bit. Commissioning reports. So all of these documents are needed when you're commissioning a project and what
They bringing in what materials are they using, and so on. Again, this we've already talked about. Here's the certification levels. If you're going, if you know you're at 100, then you're super platinum. You're like the the ideal, right? Everybody kind of wants to follow you, but even if you make it beyond 80, you're awesome
So review, so you can have like a preliminary review. It's not like where, oh man, you're done, you fail, right? No, no. You can have a preliminary review. You get some feedback, you have some questions
And then they can provide you suggestions. Hey, you have this, why don't you consider this instead? And this is why, I mean, especially if you're planning a new building, it's easy, right? But if you're kind of restoring something, you're trying to do, you can have a preliminary review
And then have the final review to get the certification. There's also an appeal process where you can say, you know, yes, this is you gave me this number, but I don't think in the audit you missed this
So I would like you to reconsider our certification. So you can also have this, what they call like an appeal process. There's a online you can have, you can track everything
Also, they have resources that they share with you, so you kind of understand
what are, one
understand the process itself, but then you can also kind of learn, like, from best practices, right?
energy, material, any of that. There's an online. You can also
gather all of this and submit it online for somebody to initially review online and provide you feedback online, and then go from there.
Right? Again, so in order to
be successful. I think one… this is for anything, any project, I would say, right? So being proactive, right? Plannerly with the integrated team, you're having a discussion with the consultant very early, and then
It's kind of like we always say, right, when we are going, what are all the low-hanging fruit
Right? So whatever is easy and it kind of already is fits with what you're doing as a company
go after those. Those are easy. That's like no-brainer, right? Why would we not do that? So get all the easy credits out of the way, and then you also want to align credits with your goal, right? So you have this project and this project, and this is your vision for your company
So does
What you want to do for your certification? Let's say, for instance, you're saying that, hey, you want to create this
The new health and wellness, like a gym slash cafeteria area at your company to improve the health and well-being of your employees. And then so you can think about, okay, what can I do
In terms of getting credits for this new plan that I have new center that I have, right? Engaging stakeholders continuously. I mean, this is why, I mean, even if
For instance, if you're working with, again.
let's say, like, furniture supplier, or like
fittings in your space, any of those, you're conveying to them also, saying, like, hey, I'm going after this, so I'm looking for, ethically sourced, locally sourced material. I'm looking for
materials where there's less no volatile organic compounds and stuff. So you're kind of conveying that so kind of everybody's working with you to help you kind of achieve this
They have what they call as an integrative process. So you're looking at, again, this is required, right? So your land that you dedicated the space and then you're kind of almost taking a pledge, right?
From being more responsible from a climate standpoint, the impact that it can have on all the occupants in the building, the carbon assessments, right, looking at what's the carbon footprint
And there's just
Considering all of those itself, and your document that's saying this is how you're taking into account all of that, then you can have a point that you're
This is why
Before you either you have an existing building, you're making some changes or you have a new building. So this is why you're having these early, early conversations with your architects, your engineers. I mean, I know Christian's an HVAC expert
So your tenants also like the occupants of the building, you're asking like, hey, what is important? You're kind of having all of these conversations with all of them and then trying to kind of then incorporate everything.
You're looking at, from a location and transportation standpoint
if you're playing this new area, it's when the building, is there access to the building? Is it walkable? I know from an urban standpoint, right, we, I know in the past we've looked
Workability, right? Workability is a measure that you can look at. Is it a transit-rich area where you have public transportation and access to the building itself? So location of the building, transportation
It's important. Also things like, do you have do you provide bike racks? Is there like subsidies that you provide if there's public transit and stuff, somebody's taking the public transport
Coming to your building. So in a way, it's
Especially if you're plotting something new, considering all of these, it can be beneficial
For your employees, too, you want happy employees at the end of the day. This is where I had mentioned earlier, if you have electric vehicles, do you have chargers for the electric vehicles? Do you have designated EV parking
Right? Things to consider. Minimum water efficiency. Again, that depending on where you are as a municipality or your state, I mean, there might be different requirements, and then based on all of that
Again, the consultant will work with you and tell you what the requirements are, and doing things like rain harvesting and stuff. But also kind of looking on the other side, right? Do you have any leaks? Do you have any sensors
That detect the leaks. So you're kind of being again proactive to see that there's no water being wasted and stuff. So just kind of being mindful, right? All of it. When you look at all of this, it can seem like common sense, but all of this common sense kind of adds up
As you progress from one little thing you do to the next little thing you do, and then as you keep going
Do you have low flow fixtures? Do you have like, so I know little things in your toilet when you're flushing right one itself, do you have the one and two flush
And then is using the minimum voting that you need for the flush? But then after that, when you after that, what happens to that water, right? Or you have a sink and then the water, are you being is that being kind of
reused, let's say you have around your building, you have a garden. So, like, here in the Student Union, right? So they have a little garden where they're growing all their vegetables and herbs and stuff that they put, and they serve
salads and stuff is the water being kind of reused for any of that you can earn points. Again, Christian's probably the expert here. So replace gas HVAC with electric heat pumps. You can earn some points
exceeding, and then for energy use again, ASHRAE has set some
baselines. And this is not. I don't know too much about it, but if you exceed what they've prescribe by 20 to 30%, then you can. You can earn points
Renewable energy, again, if you have a solar, if you have a geothermal, if you have tiny little wind, I mean all of those right Commissioning when you're commissioning the projects
And you have an interactive grid if you're producing more, you're giving back to the grid, and all of those can kind of add up. And like I said, the Tulsa Public Library with all their solar panels on the top
The energy sufficient
This is where, again, I know Michaela had mentioned solar reflectance. So I just tried to kind of look it up to see because in the general material, I didn't see where they talked much about solar reflectance
So kind of
Go ahead.
try to kind of search it and see what they had on it.
Thank you for doing that, Rita. Thank you.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, because I didn't on the general guidelines, I didn't see too much on it. And so they essentially this is where
Okay, okay.
It's a nice… no, sorry for interrupting again, Haritho. There's a nice post on this, on LinkedIn. I can share the link in our WhatsApp group
Okay, wonderful, wonderful, wonderful.
So they're talking about the solar reflectance index, right? So you're looking at the reflectance and the thermal emissivity. So they're saying that, and they have a
these numbers that they had. They're saying low slope roofs. They require that for, and then the steep slope roofs they have to have that number and then
for hardscape materials, there was the recommendation
Hmm, cool.
My wife didn't allow me to get a white roof. The compromise was a light brown. Okay
Oh, true story.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Christine, you want to talk a little bit about your roof?
Yeah, so the primary concern…
Was really the, you see the dirt much more on a white roof.
Yeah, yeah.
And so if it's a flat roof, you can't see it from the road or from next to the building, but if it's a slanted roof, you can see very well if there's rust or dirt or algae growing on it.
Right, right.
And so even with the light brown, you can still see if there is biology starting to grow in the roof, or dust accumulating.
Right, right, right, right.
And so it's maybe the question is a little bit what are we willing to accept in terms of it doesn't look quite 100% pristine and fresh and new.
I mean, the aesthetics was this
The functionality, right? And then what it does. So we're talking roofs here, but also the exterior walls, right? I mean, because again, there you have the reflectance. So I mean, if you're having what does that material need to be on the outer wall of the building and stuff
Taking that into account also
Zero waste. I mean, in theory, right? If you can not have waste
That's a good thing, and you can look at what is possible depending on try to reduce as much as as much waste as you can
reusing things, looking at low… like, this is why I was talking about the furniture. If you're getting materials that do not off gas as much, and reuse, that's that's a very big one. I mean, like I said, the student union, the countertops, the floors, all of it was kind of
Repurposed material that they used. A procurement transparency. So you're kind of talking about where you got the material from, who you got it from, but also what are their practices, right? Are they being responsible?
And so if you're getting like, let's say this bench that you put in inside an office, but where was the wood sourced from? Was it locally sourced? Was it ethically sourced, right? All of that, the transparency of
Procurement of anything waste diversion, this is again where because you are using this repurposed, you went and got this construction waste material and then you used it
for your building, right? So you're kind of earning points for waste diversion
And you're not contributing to soggy lettuce or anything else. So in the environment quality, again, so Vincent's like no smoking
But you can have indoor rack. Now we have a lot of sensors right to kind of monitor the indoor air quality. And so if you have materials choices in the spaces where you're using
being responsible for daylighting. If you have daylighting acoustics also they consider if you're using materials and because again, in the end, it's also, like, impact on occupants of the building
Post-construction air testing for VOCs. Again, nowadays, again, you have sensors, they continually monitoring the different volatile organic compounds and stuff. I know, for instance, we have a policy here at OSU
that we cannot light any incense sticks or candles and stuff
Exactly.
When there's a fire hazard, but number two, from an indoor air quality, because everything is connected since the building is closed, it's tight. And I know that Christian, yeah, no. Can you light incense there?
I don't think a lot of…
Yeah, yeah, yeah, so
And anything that's a potential fire hazard, we would get in trouble.
And incidents in Cairns, Dr. Paulette Ibert, she's a professor here. I know we did some studies with the incense sticks and kernels. Man, some of them, I mean, with our meter, I mean
especially what you call the PPM, right? Particularly
Matt is the PM 2.5. So if you have, like, 2.5 microns, those are the sneaky ones. They are there in the environment, but then they are extremely harmful, because they are so small, right? They can kind of
go in deep into your alveoli, like, and you can end up with lung cancer, right? So it's very, very, important that we are… So there's continuing… so you get points for if you're continually monitoring your air quality
If you're addressing any sustainability issues that are local, then you're trying, let's say like for instance, outside your building, let's say there is
They say that there's loss of habitat for butterflies, or loss of habitat for bees, or if you're creating something like that where you're providing something
Then maybe let's say the soil quality is not good, and then you're trying to kind of address those issues or anything the groundwater, anything that you're doing kind of beyond. The other thing is
If you have on site somebody who is LEED certified, right, lead AP, I know our interior design students, they study together and take the exam
So if you have somebody who's already has good awareness, it's a good thing, right? They can also continually kind of help you make sure that because you want to
Not just get certified, because then you have to continually maintain the status
But there's points for somebody there. Stormwater management, right? For instance, in coastal cities
Again, 110 points, we decide what you want to do, and then based on your sustainability goals.
You kind of align those and go strategically.
Again, enhanced… let's say you have a small office, fit out, and you have energy efficiency, you're being… you're kind of using that, you're using low emitting materials, and
the survey, the occupant experience, you're looking at a survey and stuff, and then you can very quickly you see it just adds up and it might be easy for you to get the gold certification, right? Retail store, if you're looking at water efficiency in the retail store
Transportation
Right, considering that if you had some materials, if you had fixtures throughout your store, you reused materials
You can quickly add up and get like a silver certification, for instance.
Again, priorities depending. And this is again very dependent on the company, dependent on your goals, dependent on your long term vision, dependent on your future projects and all of that, right? Energy, air quality
Indo, but I think
Anything that you're indirectly trying to do to improve health and well-being of your occupants, that should come back and kind of help you in the long run
Again, so retail, maybe you're focusing on water transportation materials, customer experience, right? Because if you're doing things to help improve
The customer experience, maybe your customer has an intent to spend more time because you you you
As a… I like to say, you prescribed, you're like a doctor, right? You're prescribing a good space for your consumers, for your customers who come into your retail environment, and because you took so much care
Right. And in all the material choices, the fixer choices, transportation wise, they're able to easily go there. You're reusing water. And you're also talking about all of this, right? And if they buy into it, it's possible that they spend more time there and spend more money in your store
Right? So that in itself, there's an indirect benefit when you do some so you can also very selfishly think about
in the long run right you doing all of this
can have, you can reap benefits in other ways
Right? Healthcare. This is very big, right? In the healthcare, air quality, because
hospital bone illnesses
That is a bigger problem than sometimes you go in, you have a fractured rib. You are in an accident and you go there, and you're supposed to be there for three, four days
And we are slowly beginning to hear, and then with the air circulation, and then you catch something else, and then you end up with pneumonia, right? So that's scary. So this is why
If you are monitoring your air quality, right, and you're kind of being responsible, right, accessibility is another one, right?
If you have a bariatric patient
Is there good accessibility for the bariatric patient to go in there, thinking about resilience
This is, again, like, yesterday we talked about biophilic design.
Visual connection with nature, airflow variability, but at the same time you're monitoring the air, all of it. And if you're incorporating any of these
And if it results in
Patience… excuse me
Oh, sorry, just give me one second
Oh, admitting a student.
At the end of the day
If you're able to reduce the cost for a patient because they have to stay fewer days, right? So it's both. It's one for the patient, the patient's more happy. Number two, the government's more happy because if the government is paying a part of
Healthcare cost, you're reducing the burden on the government. So you can see, like, how little things can have a large impact on society itself, for instance.
Right? But you taking these preventive measures and you being proactive right? You're improving, let's say, quality of life for people. You're reducing workers' compensation because they are able to return to work sooner
So many… there's, like, this domino effect when you be proactive and incorporate all of the changes and being responsible in the environment
In education settings, if you have daylighting, if you have visual connection to nature, I mean, going back to the bioflick side, right? The experience of the students in the classrooms. You have, for instance, representations of your Fibonacci series
You have your golden ratio incorporation of those in the spaces. I mean, studies have shown those help with improved information retention
Right? The reduction of cognitive load. So when Dr. Bach is teaching in the class, just having these design interventions in a classroom
Right? Can help students kind of learn the material better, right? Because sometimes as professors, I mean, you can do your best to try to convey, but
Because
it because it it it feels like the airflow is not good, and it feels like the air is stagnant in the space right? So when when you enter the classroom, you feel like your eyes are watering
you feel like you have a headache
Right? And then number two, it's it's in the basement, right? So maybe there was some water leak and there was some mold buildup. and then that mold that becomes airborne
That's affecting as you breathe in the air in the classroom.
Right? And then you're in the basement, there's no access to sunlight
And then you wonder why students are not performing well. You wonder why students are not showing up to class.
Right? So these Christian's laughing.
We put our research students into the second floor below ground.
Oh, no.
And I had one student that really wanted to get away from this location, and he wasn't allowed to, so I was very, very upset about that.
But yeah, anyways, it's the research students often end up in spaces that aren't super welcoming.
Right, right, right, right, right, right. I mean, but let's say there is a basement, you're two floors down, right?
What can we do, right? What interventions can we introduce? When can we have a good indoor air quality sensor, make sure number two, can we have like we were talking yesterday, can you have
Like
From the solar factory, you have a screen, you have digital screens showing movement of the clouds. You have a wall here, a digital wall. Whatever is possible, or you have paintings with representation of your golden ratio, Fibonacci series
Whatever that is right to kind of help help help them
There can be some challenges sometimes. Some credits, they can overlap with the prerequisites. Documentation, this can be challenging
But I think once you have the system in place, then it's easy. This is why if you have the lead AP person on the team already, it's easy.
Sometimes trade-offs are required, but if you have a consultant. But again, like you said, even if you don't want to pay for all of this and pay this large money, you can still incorporate all of the principles
the underlying principles. If you still don't want to kind of go
Maximize the points, again, like, this, again, I said this earlier
Start with the easy credit. It's easy. Now, OSU, for us here on our campus, our entire campus has a no-smoking policy
If you want to smoke, you have to leave the campus
That's an easy thing to implement, right? It's a policy that you do. And then low flow fixtures. These are all… you're just kind of saying, if we have these fixtures along with some sensors
I think it's easy to convince
A business convince an organization
to incorporate to to to invest some money. If you show them the cost benefits, saying that a what's the return on investment? Right? You say, like, you're going to spend 10,000 now in 3 years you're going to be saving 30,000
Right? That's an easy way to make an argument.
Right. Pursue high value credits. So energy efficiency, material transparen, I mean, transparency. I think all of us for anything, we should be transparent about it.
And remember yesterday I talked about when you pay the dollar, right, when you put the dollar down, so you're buying any material, you're buying… you're buying furniture. I think if you are responsible
If you are the designer and you put the dollar down, and you buy a piece of furniture, but that furniture, the company that you brought it from
They were responsible for
wiping out
a lot of trees on our planet. Number two, they were doing this in a very sensitive area where it was very important to
have as many trees as possible. They could care less. But you paid the money, right? And then also as they were manufacturing it, they were using non-renewable energy in their manufacturing plant to make the furniture
Right? And then you have all of these chemicals that were used. Your furniture was doused in these chemicals. And then you bought the furniture and then you put it in the hospital, or you put it in the classroom.
and you were not transparent
Right?
I think, boy, that's a tough one, right? But on the other hand, if you are transparent and if it's helping students learn better, if it's helping patients learn better, if it's helping customers spend more time in your store
Where they're not tearing up, I can swear there's a Christian, I know we played the racquetball in Colwyn on the bottom.
We should do so again.
Hmm…
Okay.
Right? But I can swear, Christian, when I go into that space, my eyes start tearing, you know? But when I leave that space, my eyes are, I start tearing and then my nose, I mean, it just doesn't feel good when I go there, because it's in the basement, it's on the side there. I always suspect that the air quality is not good there
Yeah, that makes sense.
Yeah, yeah. Anyways, you can use an integrated design process to maximize your points. I mean, this building certifications, I mean, this is globally used, right? Not here in the US. I mean
They have record of different countries, at least different buildings in different countries, so many countries have used it. Again, linked to property value premiums, encourage policy and incentive programs
Again, the upfront cost usually
But like I said, if you can talk about it from a return on investment standpoint
then yes, but if you just look at it and just tell somebody, hey, we need to get LEED certified, I need you to spend $40,000. You're like, what? No, we don't have that kind of a budget
Right, but then you break it down and explain, hey, here's how much you're going to be saving in the long run
Then somebody can tell you, all right, we'll follow some of the principles, but we're not going to pay somebody large amount of money to do this. You still internally do it, right?
But you document your workload regional adaptation. Sometimes there might be restrictions. I know without taking names and being political. I've heard that some places
For instance, if you have solar or wind energy, you have to pay a surcharge, and you have to pay more money back to the government
I'll leave it at that and try not to get too political
The future of this, again, more carbon neutrality. This one right smart buildings and AI, they talk about AI is in everything, right? And it's true because it's learning the building more and more, right? As you go and you essentially just some code
Yeah, you're right. You're saying if this happens, do this, this happens, do this, and that's just continually learning it. and then if if
If you do not, it's like your occupancy sensor in a way, right? When you say if there are zero individuals, if there's no
Like shut the airflow there like whatever your response is, right? More and more, I mean, again, with your smart sensors, it's all integrated there. It's kind of learning you more and adapting by itself.
Right
Emphasis on resilience and equity. Sorry
So, in a way, you can look at it as a framework for measuring sustainability
Interiors, looking at occupancy. Considering both the environment and the economic benefits. Remember yesterday we talked about PPP
People, planet, profit. You're considering all of that in a way, right? You're looking at the occupants of a building. You're looking at all the environmental factors, and then you're looking at the money because that is important
Sorry, let me go back one. So
In a way, green buildings, if you think about it as healthier people, healthier planet, why not?
Right? So that's in a nutshell. So let's take a little break. It's 9:15. And then
And if anybody has any let's take a five minute break. Let's take a five minute break, and then when you come back, you can… if you think of any questions, please let me know.
And then we'll answer the questions, and then we'll slowly get into well
and talk on the other side.
And we'll watch Jessica Green's talk on the sampling air and designing for
Being intentional
For good air quality
There's a good movie I thought about
This might be good for… if you want to watch
Okay,
We can get started again if everybody's okay. I just, in the chat, I put a link to a documentary. It's called Greening of Saudi
It's a pretty good document, but I watched it several years ago, but it's a really good example of
how there's this building in Boston, and they were going after LEED certification
And as they are pursuing the lead certification, different challenges that they face and stuff, it's really interesting. So they had, like, a weed board cabinetry to recycle steel, bamboo flooring, dual flush toilets
And then they run into issues. They were sourcing some materials from outside the country. It kind
gives you, like.
like, a good insight on pursuing lead itself. So if you have the time, when you have the time, please try and watch that documentary.
All right. Does anybody have any questions?
Okay.
Not on this.
No? Okay. Okay, okay. So let's, we'll watch that the air quality talk. We'll talk a little bit, and then we'll jump into well.
All right
Sure enough, they have advertisements for everything now.
Just a second.
discovered an invisible ecosystems made of tiny life forms, bacteria, viruses, fungi
Our desks, our computers, our fences, buildings all harbor resident microbial landscapes.
As we design these things, we could be thinking about designing these invisible worlds and also thinking about how they interact with our personal ecosystem
Our bodies are home to trillions of microbes, and these creatures define who we are
the microbes in your gut can influence your weight and your moods. The microbes on your skin can help boost your immune system. The microbes in your mouth can freshen your breath
And the key thing is that our personal ecosystems interact with ecosystems on everything we touch. So, for example, when you touch a pencil, microbial exchange happens.
If we can't design invisible ecosystems in our surroundings, this opens a path to influencing our health in unprecedented ways.
I get asked all of the time from people, is it possible to really design microbial ecosystems?
And I believe the answer is yes
I think we're doing it right now, but we're doing it unconsciously
I'm going to share data with you from one aspect of my research focused on architecture that demonstrates how through both conscious and unconscious design, we're impacting these invisible worlds.
This is the Willis Business Complex at the University of Oregon. And I work with a team of architects and biologists to sample over 300 rooms in this building.
We wanted to get something like a fossil record for building, and to do this, we sampled dust
From the dust, we pulled out bacterial cells, broke them open and compared their gene sequences.
This means that people in my group were doing a lot of vacuuming during this project
This is a picture of Tim, who, right when I snapped this picture, reminded me, he said, Jessica, the last lab group I worked in, I was doing field work in the Costa Rican rainforest, and things have changed dramatically for me.
So I'm going to show you now first what we found in the offices, and we're going to look at the data through a visualization tool that I've been working on in partnership with Autodesk.
The way that you look at this data is first look around the outside of the circle. You'll see broad bacterial groups. And if you look at the shape of this pink lobe, it tells you something about the relative abundance of each food
So at 12 o'clock, you'll see that offices have a lot of alpha proteobacteria, and at 1 o'clock you'll see that bacilli are relatively rare
Let's take a look at what's going on in different space types in this building. If you look inside the restrooms, they all have really similar ecosystems. And if you were to look inside the classrooms, those also have similar ecosystems. But if you look
across these space types, you can see that they're fundamentally different from one another
I like to think of bathrooms like a tropical rainforest. I told Tim if you could just see the microbes, it's kind of like being in Costa Rica. Kind of.
And I also like to think of offices being a temperate grassland.
This perspective is a really powerful one for designers. Because you can bring on principles of ecology. And a really important principle ecology is dispersal.
The way organisms move around. We know that microbes are dispersed around by people and by air. So the very 1st thing we wanted to do in this building was look at the air system.
Mechanical engineers design air handling units to make sure that people are comfortable, that the airflow and temperature is just right. They do this using principles of physics and chemistry, but they could also be using biology
If you look at the microbes in one of the air handling units in this building, you'll see that they're all very similar to one another
And if you compare this to the microbes in a different air handling unit, you'll see that they're fundamentally different.
The rooms in this building are like islands in an archipelago. And what that means is that mechanical engineers are like eco engineers and they have the ability to structure biomes in this building the way that they want to.
Another facet of how microbes get around is by people, and designers often cluster rooms together to facilitate interactions among people or the sharing of ideas, like in labs and in offices.
Given that microbes travel around with people, you might expect to see rooms that are close together have really similar biomes
and that is exactly what we found. If you look at classrooms right adjacent to one another, they have very different ecosystems. But if you go to a class, sorry, an office that is a farther walking distance away, the ecosystem is fundamentally different
And when I see the power that dispersal has on these biogeographic patterns, it makes me think that it's possible to
tackle really challenging problems like hospital acquired infections
This has got to be in part of building ecology problem.
I'm going to tell you one more story about this building.
I am collaborating with Charlie Brown. He's an architect. And Charlie is deeply concerned about global climate change. He's dedicated his life to sustainable design
When he met me and realized that it was possible for him to study in a quantitative way how his design choices impacted the ecology and biology of this building, he got really excited because it added a new dimension to what he did. He went from thinking just about energy to also
Starting to think about human health.
He helped design some of the area handling systems in this building and the way it was ventilated. So what I'm 1st going to show you is air that we sampled outside of the building
What you're looking at is a signature of bacterial communities and outdoor air and how they vary over time.
Next, I'm going to show you what happened when we experimentally manipulated classrooms. We blocked them off at night so that they got no ventilation. A lot of buildings are operated this way, probably where you work, and companies do this to save money on their energy bill
What we found is these wounds remained relatively stagnant until Saturday when we opened the vents up again.
When you walk into those rooms, they smelled really bad, and our data suggests that it has something to do with leaving behind the airborne bacterial seed from people the day before.
Contrast this to rooms that were designed using a sustainable passive design strategy where air came in from the outside the Ubers
In these rooms, the air track the outdoor air relatively well, and when Charlie saw this, he got really excited. He felt like he had made a good choice with the design process
Because it was both energy efficient and it washed away the building's resident microbial landscape.
The examples that I just gave you are about architecture, but they're relevant to the design of anything.
Imagine designing with the kinds of microbes that we want in a plane.
or on a phone
There's a new microbe I just discovered it, it's called GLIS, and it's been shown to both ward off pathogens and give you good rest.
Wouldn't it be awesome if we all had bliss in our phones?
A conscious approach to design. I'm calling it bio-informed design, and I think it's possible. Thank you.
Any thoughts, anybody?
No thoughts
Okay, I'll show you one little thing, and then we can go
Let me see
I mean, I think doing things like this, right? So in this case, it's a very simple example where she showed that if you have stagnant air
And if that can have a negative impact on students, there's a hidden cost associated with it
Right? So I think it's important to consider things like that. When we are talking about investment to improve
have design interventions in a space
to improve the health and well-being of individuals who might use the space. Think of it the other way in terms of if you don't do it, what are all the hidden costs associated with that?
As it leads to poor health and well-being
So
Let me go back here. This is just talking about materials in a space. This was a study that we did and you can see
Let's see if we make it bigger
So for instance, if you have spray paint
I mean, look at that rate parts per billion, 13,342. That's crazy.
20 is the accepted length. Then CO2 in terms of the PPMs, if you're having like paint, if you're having a wood stain
So we have to be mindful of
Anything that we use in a space, and how that might affect anybody who might use that space. Anyway, I thought I'd just share this, because we'd done a study some time back looking at different materials that are used in the space
Okay, let's go back. Oops, not there
Let's go back to
Okay.
Let's switch gears a little bit and talk about well. This is kind of because when I think when we're talking about occupants and their health and well-being within a space and stuff, it's also important.
This is more from a health perspective than from the building perspective, right? So it's a performance-based system for measuring features of the build environment with the focus on health and wellbeing
Right? Developed by this company. It works alongside lead and other green building systems. That's why I kind of wanted to, since we're talking about LEED, I thought it'd be good to kind of
talk a little bit about this too
2014 was when they developed the standard first and then they released an agenda in 2016.
Again, focuses human health and comfort. So you're going beyond just sustainability and really, really diving deep. The core is the people, anybody who is using any space
How do we
come up with anything with the central focus of improving health and well-being, right? But it's… and it's not just physical, right? You're going beyond that. You're thinking mental health is important
Social well-being is important
I think this is especially important as we think about
All of us, right, as we age in some of us maybe halfway there
Right in life, maybe a little
A little over that and maybe 20, 30 years as we maybe hit 80.
If you think about aging in place, it's very, very for us, I mean, here in interior design, it's a very important concept for us as designers, as researchers
How do we help individuals gracefully age
Right?
And for that, again, the physical and for aging in place, I mean the physical health is absolutely important. Mental health is absolutely important. Number three, social interaction, right? We as humans, we are social beings
Are we designing to provide opportunities for us to continue to be social beings? Because if that is very, very it's one of the key factors
For us to maintain a quality of life and especially carry out the instrumented activities of daily living as we age
And now there is more awareness, right? With more awareness, there is
higher demand now for healthy buildings. So why not
use some of the principles of well
to improve, enhance the spaces that we are in again, because most of us spend majority of our day inside the built environment.
Again, just like with LEED, there's a registration process, you identify some preconditions again. These are like non-negotiable. You have to have them. Then you select some optimizations, whatever you want to
Then there's a documentation, there's a verification. And then again, there's a certification. I mean, so you see parallels between this and LEED.
Right.
Silver, you've met all the preconditions, gold, you've met the preconditions, and you have
kind of
where you can pick and choose, right? You want the strawberry and the blueberry and blackberry and whatever you want, right? You're kind of choosing, right? Some of the preconditions, you're choosing… sorry, the preconditions and some of what you want to optimize. So 40
Platinum majority of so your fruit basket is almost full, right, so to speak. And then you have the recertification process every three years
You can do this with new and existing buildings. You can also do it with the new and existing interiors. You can do it with the coal and the shell of the building. And again, they've done
certifications across different industries, right? They can do it for the education sector, the retail sector, the healthcare sector, residential, you're staying at home
Hospitality, right? Pretty much a lot of the
buildings that most of us as humans spend time in our lives
So from an air quality standpoint, so I just talked about air quality. Jessica Green, I mean
And then I showed you examples of the materials and our. So the goal is to again have
high air quality, but
Again, to me, but what does
having high quality mean
But I think it depends, right? Again, because we have some
recommendations, and in terms of… so with the total volatile organic compounds, not having more than 20 parts per million exposure. So just like that, I mean, different, different things. But there are simple things that you can do
Right? For indoor air quality, for instance, do you have a good filtering system?
Number two, do you have good airflow?
Number three, are you doing air sampling regularly and testing periodically?
Number 4, do you have sensors that are continually monitoring it and then because when you have the monitoring that you do
But then you also have when experts come like Jessica, they come and do the air sampling, take it to a lab and they give you a report. Are you doing that on an annual basis, for instance? Just like we have here in Oklahoma State University campus, do you have a smoking ban
Again, ventilation design. Are you in a tight building or is there an opportunity for airflow?
with the windows open or not. I mean, all of these things you need to kind of consider.
Optimizations. So this is like your minimum is you need to have some level of a quality standard. The smoking man and you have, whether it's artificial or natural, you have a good ventilation system in place
Right? So this is saying that's preconditions. Then you kind of add the toppings. So now you have your vanilla ice cream and now on the top you you need to put the toppings if you want to move up right you have an enhanced filtration system
You have a good air quality monitoring system and you have good cleaning protocols in space.
Right? Now, when you say cleaning protocols, let's take this from a healthcare standpoint. Let's say you
have orders, right?
in a room, and if you're using, let's say, air fresheners to try and
Please, please pay attention carefully to these next few words that I choose, right? You're using air fresheners not to clean the air
to mask the odors
Again, we've done some studies. So if you take your Febries and what they call as air fresheners in spaces
Man, the, the
The PPM values, the CO2 values, it is crazy. You won't believe if any of you, I mean, just on a side note, if you are using afresh give you a headache. Yeah, Christian, absolutely
Right? If you're using And sometimes you have these plugin air fresheners that they put in the space. I mean, to me, it's a sin. I mean, if you actually go and record the ag quality value, because we did it, I mean, it's crazy. It's really, really bad for your health
Everything that you put inside and
Yeah, see, you don't have a Dex, and you're getting it. It's kind of similarly with the SIG building, right? You don't have any symptoms. Oftentimes, we are… we are good doctors in ourselves, because we are good sensors, right? So if you go to the space
And you are experiencing nauseousness. If you are experiencing your eyes are watery right, you feel lightheaded. I mean, a lot of these
They could be symptoms to an underlying problem. In this case, the air quality right? And if you so if you're having cleaning protocols, let's say you are also using cleaning wipes with chemicals right, and you have this there. And and what if
They go airborne. There's so many things that we need to kind of consider. So every decision that we as a human make
When we think we're doing something good by putting an air freshener or putting… using cleaning materials that are not appropriate, right?
that can kind of
indirectly come back to haunt us. So we need to be very mindful. And this is why talking about transparency earlier, for cleaning protocols, the cleaning materials that you use, do you have transparency on the materials that you use? Because if you don't have transparency on the materials
That's not good. Because again, you kind of if you're in a hospital setting, you are literally like playing with people's lives. And we should be mindful of that.
You can have, for instance, HMO filters, VOC reduction, IQ sensors, right? So these are all things that you can kind of integrate into your space to help improve the air quality
And indirectly help improve the health and well-being of the occupants.
From a water standpoint, do you provide safe and clean drinking water?
So we here at OSU, the entire campus, we have these fountains in all the buildings, right? And then, you know, I've got my water bottle. You can go back and fill it. And they have a we have a central
station where the water comes from, and they have, like, multi-layers of filtering that they use, and then they monitor the water as they come through the pipes
to the different water stations that we have. And so are we providing something like that? If you're not and are you monitoring it and and
Throughout
And in a way, you also preventing this more and more plastic right from people buying plastic water. And then you have the little
particulates from the plastic that you might be indirectly consuming without knowing it, and if that's affecting you. So, things like that, right? So you have very clear intention. It's all about the health and well-being of the people, because if you're providing water is a basic necessity, right? All of us
need to be drinking water, hydrate, and especially now it's really hot
Every day, and that's a basic need, and if you're kind of providing that
That's a good thing, right? So you're doing the water quality testing periodically, looking at any contaminants, and if there are any contaminants, what are some guidelines that were set in terms of it cannot go above a certain level
Are you meeting those conditions? Now, now adding the cherry on the top, right? Do you have an advanced filtration system
Do you have a water quality promotion program at your institution? If not, it's a good, good. This is the basic thing you can do, right? Provide good water.
So then, do you have, for instance, like, a reverse osmosis system
Again, hydration stations. Hydration stations actually Christian, I'm not sure if you know, if you knew how they came about
No idea.
It's very interesting, actually. Several years ago.
One of the students, because the sustainability office would give out money for any student-led initiatives on campus. And one of the student proposed
this water station
In just one building, right? And I think they gave $5,000, and they implemented this water station. Then another building wanted it, another building, and that's how then it flooded. So it was a student led
initiative that led to us now having water stations across campus. So I thought it was a very kind of almost proud of the students who initiated this effort and now as a result, we all have
It's been a few several years now, but it was good to know that it was a student-led initiative.
From a nourishment standpoint, again, encouraging healthy eating habits. So if you
an institution and an organization, and you have a cafeteria
Is it McDonald's or is it like Chick-fil-A we have here on campus? But you also have, are you providing healthy options to eat, right?
Here in Oklahoma, unfortunately, we are a poor state. We have
These
food deserts
Unfortunately. And
Obesity is very high, and in certain places, there are more dialysis centers
Then healthy stores where you can get healthy food.
But so these are things, right? So if you're long-term health and well-being of your employees are important to you, just like
One of the restaurants in the Student Union
using the rainwater harvesting and everything, they're growing their own herbs, own vegetables, and using fresh produce, fresh salad to serve you meals. That's amazing.
Right? So just like that, it's important. So if you… you can earn some points just encouraging healthy habits, but then when you go down to your preconditions.
the fruits, vegetables are available
The food is clearly labeled and everything on there. There's nothing hidden, right? There's transparency on the labeling on the food
There's transparency on the allergens in the food
Right? That's meeting the preconditions, optimization, portion control. Maybe when you are selling the meals, it's smaller portions as opposed to larger
Sister lives in the Netherlands, and I think in November I might be visiting her
Okay.
When I go there, portion size is small. It's a good thing. When I come back here in the US, it's like two times the portion size that we get over there. It's crazy here.
Right? Do you have organic produce? Do you have mindful eating spaces
This is very, very important. I know for me, I just eat in my office. Sometimes I'm not paying attention to what I eat
But if health and well-being, it's amazing that the standard is going to that level where you are thinking about in your institution, in your organization, in your company, do you have a place where you can
not be on this
necessarily evil, or on your tablet, or on the computer, and then just where we're taking a bite
without even thinking about what we eat
Christine, go ahead
Yeah, yeah, I was…
I was just thinking it's like part of it is, is what you eat, it has gotten much, much more highly processed.
And the other thing is when I was with my grandparents, when I was little.
They will always pray before they ate, and so be grateful for the food.
Um, and I had a non-religious friend that
did a very similar thing. It was before he started to eat, you took a quick break, closed your eyes, and were grateful for the food.
And now it's like you you you eat some highly processed.
Garbage, junk food.
When you watch your video stuff on your cell phone in parallel, and you don't even pay attention to what you eat, and you're not grateful for it either.
Oh, that's what…
So I think there's something that we can get back to that other people already had figured out.
Mm-hmm.
No, no, absolutely, totally, totally. I mean, for me also, Christian, I mean, in a boarding school grade three to grade 12, 10 years there. Before Amira, we always said this little prayer. We always said, Lord, thank you for this
Uh-huh.
food that you've given us, and I mean, we really appreciate it. And then we ate. So I think you're right, we need to kind of go back to those, maybe, and then even here on campus, I mean, because everybody's on the run, they just… I mean, I'm guilty, right? I just sit
Exactly.
And then I'm just one hand, I'm eating, the one hand is still typing something, or I'm watching, like, reading an article or something.
Right.
And then the food falls into your keyboard over the years and you need to replace the keyboard every two years because it doesn't work anymore.
Hello, Dixon.
Yeah, I'm looking at my ego, there's probably some breadcrumbs there. Not good, not good, right? But I hope we can be more mindful and kind of it was really neat to see this being brought up
So cafeteria offering. It's good to see some of our schools here locally. Now they're providing more fruit
add more vegetables as opposed to just know when I go at least some places, there's some fruit available or there's some fresh fruit they're using
To give you, like, fresh juice or something like that, but so having these healthy choices are important
From a light, do you have is it supporting circadian health and productivity? And we all have sleep cycles
Do you have the right light and need to absolutely consider it. Do you have minimum daylighting? Do you have black control right? It's little things, but I mean, if it's
If it's affecting individuals and if there's glare in a space, I mean, that's absolutely a no-no.
We should not have that, right? And then nowadays it's easier with the smart lighting systems. We have an amazing professor here in our department, Dr. Paulette Ebert. She is a lighting expert. She's a full professor. She's
done so many… she's also served as consultants to companies, you know, like, if you were, let's say, if you're an air traffic controller.
If you're working in a nuclear power station
If you're a healthcare worker, if you work… if you're a meat care worker working a 24-hour, you're one of three teams that work over 24 hours
And you're working the late night shift. I mean, what lighting should be appropriate. And she's provided some good advice to different companies and it's very important, I think, that we consider it's very underrated, I think, light
Right? So it's
Again, because we have the technology now, your tunable LED lighting, we have larger windows for your daylighting if you can. It's absolutely crucial that we have
Because all of us, we are kind of we are very visual beings. We primarily kind of see things. Most of our input comes from our vision, from our eyes. And if we are not having either daylighting or good lighting
To kind of help us be productive and efficient, but instead if you're having bad lighting that is indirectly taxing us. And if our cognitive load
is higher just because we are in a space with inappropriate lighting
Boy, that's completely opposite to trying to take care of or want to invest in the human being and be invested in the health and well-being from a productivity standpoint, from a creativity standpoint, from
You want, if the employees are doing well and you provide them with the best interventions, why not?
Right?
Physical fitness. Do you have space? Have you
thought about, right? Promoting physical activity and fitness. It doesn't mean you need to have a full-fledged gym with dumbbells and everything. Sometimes it… all it might mean is that you have signage beside the elevator. We have a signage beside the elevator downstairs
Saying that, hey, if you take the stairs, you can burn this many calories, right? And you encourage, you encourage stair use, for instance, and make sure that the stair access is good
Make sure that it's maintained well, make sure that there's no tripping hazards on the stairs. That whenever the every night the cleaning crew when they go through it
Yesterday, when I came in early, the stairs outside the building, actually, they had soapy water on it. I… and it was… I said, man, that's a real… my dissertation was on biomechanics of slips and falls in older adult
Man, you have a slippery surface. You're asking for trouble. That's a lawsuit.
Right? So… but can you… can you can you be intentional about
space and can you have walkways
Just inside the building, just outside the building where you are kind of promoting walking, right? And then maybe you have some policies in place also. So because there's one you can have design interventions, right?
We always say engineering interventions, design interventions, that should be your number one
That's the first step, right? That's the 1st approach. Absolutely, I agree 100%. But second, I also think you can have administrative policies in place to help improve health and well-being, right? You can have little reminders
Telling everybody, hey, if you're seated for what now? I've been sitting for like two hours after this two and a half, I need to go for a walk, right? That needs we have worker cycles, but rest doesn't mean
Going out and smoking a cigarette, right? Rest could just mean me getting up here
walking to the main office, meeting with
the administrative personnel in the main office, right? It could also mean me working through my lab
Right? And then so all of these need to kind of be built in. So you have some of it well is through the design interventions, but I think some of it can also be policies that you set in Spain, set in place so that you can achieve this
If you have fitness spaces, formal, informal fitness space. So our lounge area, maybe the lounge area at noon
becomes a yoga space for our students. Why not?
Right? Active design. Do you have design such that you're promoting activity as opposed to hampering the activity? I know Miss Delena right across, she works in the office
She has an awesome look, but I know Christian has an awesome sit-stand desk in his office too
Right? So you have a entire studio for interior design in the 4th floor and the 3rd floor. 2 years ago we changed all of the workstations, and now all of the workstations are sit, stand workstations, because
Sometimes students are drafting, rendering, it can take hours. So they have the option if they want to sit, if they want to stand, however they feel comfortable, because it's important that we give them the flexibility so that they can work however they want
Central Serge is a standing desk, like I was telling you about Christian uses. If you have a gym facility here on campus, we have a Colvin Center, and it's free for all of us as faculty and staff, you know, to use, so there's no cost associated with it. We can just walk in there and exercise
Anytime you want to
Enhancing comfort and accessibility. Again, comfort
It's a very subjective term, because when we say comfort, we usually talk perceived comfort
So what does how do you define comfort again? So you do some precedent studies and figure out
How are you going to for instance, comfort of chairs, right? They've done some studies on how you assess the comfort of the chairs. You have them individuals do reading, writing different tasks
And then you look at their perceived comfort, you have a subjective rating scale. Accessibility. Again, if somebody is in a wheelchair, do they have access to the classroom? So in the classroom, in my classroom, right across that door
We have a larger bench at the back, sorry, a larger table. Otherwise.
Majority of the seating in that classroom is a combined chair and desk. We have a chair and you just fold out
the death part of it, and you ride on it. But at the back of it, we have a large table, so if somebody is in a wheelchair, they can come and pull in and sit there. So things like that. Are you making all the necessary accommodations that you have to
Acoustic control
I mean, this is very, very important, right? So that we consider the acoustic properties of the spaces that we are in. I know one of the professions, because this classroom
Right across my door
is adjacent to all our offices, and especially the offices that are behind that classroom
Some of the sound was going in from there to the offices. There's three offices behind that classroom, and some of the
faculty were being affected by they were not able to focus and really get work done. So then we're thinking about, okay, what what acoustic panels can we have in place? How do we try to soundproof this place
So that other people who are in adjacent spaces are not affected by it
ergonomics for me, I mean, I'm an ergonomist. I always like to say that simply put, it's designed for human use, right? Another way to look at it is, are we matching capabilities and limitations of individuals to demands of the task
Right? So if my task here is primarily sitting and typing
Is and
I have back issues
Is my chair proper? And then if I have wrist, do I have a wrist? So for me, I have an ergonomic wrist support. I have my
Mouse pad with the wrist support
and I have my
And I can move things around and I have an ergonomic chair right trying to kind of help me be functional in this space
Mm-hmm.
So you can think about thermal comfort for us, unfortunately, in a Christian can say, we usually don't have a say in this. So I have my extra fan or if it's cooler than in the winter, then I have two extra jackets
But it's important, right? If we can try to provide thermal comfort because there's again studies showing if you're working in the optimum temperature
That you can be more productive and stuff.
Yeah, I should say.
Go ahead, Christian
Well, I want to mention on the productivity side, most of the cost for buildings in the US is really the people working there, not the energy.
And so it all gets back to the OK insulated closed box would be the optimum, but really we got to keep the people productive and healthy.
Right, right, right, right, challenge
Do you have accessible design features to make any accommodations? I was just talking about sound soundproofing, right? Of the classroom so that others are not affected by it. Do you have? Are you following universal design principles
One thing I can think about is in some spaces, you have your flooring, right? And then you have a carpet. And then somebody is coming in a wheelchair. They are forced to work harder to try to go over the carpet
If the carpet is recessed into the floor
Right? Then it's easy for them to just kind of transition easily
from there to the carpet, right? Little things like that. I mean, are we being mindful?
As we design
talking about the mind, supporting mental health and well-being, this is a very, very big issue, you know, especially here on campuses. I think ever since COVID
Mental health has really become a focus because we have students. I know I was serving on a committee earlier at the university called the Reinstatement Committee
And boy, a lot of students are struggling with their mental health
And so how can we be more intentional in
Creating design interventions and creating policies so that students are able to not so that they don't stress out as much. Like earlier we talked about can we have
good color, good lighting, can we have access… can we have biophilic design principles? All of that
To help with the mental health and well-being of the students.
Right? So health awareness
One
I think this is why it's important to do periodic reviews right? We do
And I always like to do
We don't wait till the end of the semester to do a review, right? You do a we do what we call formative evaluations. This is where you do an evaluation early to check
You don't wait till the year end to see, hey, how did everybody do? No, that's the wrong approach, right? You should be proactive. Week 2, week 3, right? Your new year has started week two, week 3, you go in, and then
Figure out if there are any challenges that need to be addressed so you can address it right then and there, instead of coming back at the end and saying, Oh
Sorry, you faced all of these issues? My bad.
I hope that next year you
No, you go in and fix it in the first place, right? Biophilic design principles, again, like I said, visual connection, non-visual connection, thermal airflow variability, having biomorphic forms, material connection with nature
Right? Any of that, it's it's
And then I have a little I have this usually students
I don't know what I did to show you this
I have this here in my office. Usually when students are coming in
They usually like raking this and and oh they're just holding that and they feel like they have a material connection with nature usually I don't know they and then the window I have some little plants there and
It's
It's important, right, that we do the little things so that our students can do well. Do we have stress management programs? And yes, the campus has amazing resources
Sleep slow boot, sleep is very underrated, right? I usually post the question to my students. I try to scare them. I try to tell them that each night you do not sleep well, you're increasing your chances of getting dementia
Right? But do you have a good program in the company? This is again, so I think the well program, it starts really like diving deep into the human being
And
asking us these questions, do you have all of these in place to really take care of
your occupants, whoever is using whatever space. Indo greenery, we're seeing more and more of this. I think especially, I think even in retail environments, right?
is where you're providing this. So
It's about enhancing the experience for individuals in the space.
Again, there's tons of literature talking about we have the indoor greenery, how that benefits individuals, helps calm them down
less stress. Meditation rooms. Yes, they also have some meditation rooms. Christine, I'm not sure if you've seen or been to the biofeedback room that they have here on campus
No.
And the student health center. So you can go in, Christine, and you put the clip around and it's looking at your heart rate.
Hmm.
And then on the screen, it's just like an outdoor environment with grass. And then
Uh-huh.
When you start calming down like a rabbit comes out to play
And then you get more calm, then there's like rabbits and deer, like there's different things. So it's like this biofeedback
Hmm, interesting.
Right? So it's good to see that they have something like that to help students.
They have good wellness policies. They always have the offices open. And again, Colvin Wellness Center is really good. They have group exercise classes, for instance.
You have dance classes, you have your… I know one of my students, she was, you know, with your
What do they call it with your biking
spin spin classes
She was an instructor since she was a sprint instructor.
Scoring well again, so your preconditions must be met to achieve your certification
Your optimizations, again, they provide the additional recognitions that you need. Again, higher level you need, again, more more optimizations. You're meeting the base, and then you're having much more that you can try to kind of take forward
And your scorecards, they show compliance across different concepts
And this is where, right? I mean, in terms of points, you're looking at… you're focusing on air
Again, big emphasis there right on air quality. That's why earlier we was talking about air and air quality. It is important. We don't realize it. All of us breathe. If we don't breathe, we die, right? So
But the air that we take in
It's very, very vital, right, for our health and well-being. Water. So we talked about water, like, do you have
Clean water, access to good water that anybody can have and so that you kind of it's a basic need. A nourishment. So we talked about if you're having cafes, are you providing healthy food? Again, Student Union
I mentioned earlier, right? You're having the rainwater harvesting, you're growing the vegetables, and you're taking those vegetables rich in nutrients and students are eating that as opposed to
the fast food, which is not good. And if that is affecting
Physical health indirectly affecting mental health, and then… but I think nourishment also kind of goes back to
This is why we provide lunch breaks, right? So that you can take time to mindfully eat. And I know I need to do better because here I'll be honest with you.
I'm not even
That's my bread
Right
Sometimes I'm busy, I don't have time
I just do a squeeze of peanut butter and I'm not even looking. I'm just eating it. But good part is I have my water bottle with me all the time
And but… so, one… and I think, well, that's the thing, is one is it's not just do you have a space where you can
Eat mindfully.
They're extending that, saying that you have
Do you have
We need to put out on your diet, okay?
But
And it's a comment.
I think Christians are on a program, he's doing a study with the nutrition department
So
I feel sorry for them because I'm such an outlier.
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, you have your own garden and everything you eat more healthy, man.
Attempting to do some sins in between.
Yeah, I participated in a study there too on sometime back. It's last year, I think
Hmm, hmm.
But they had another study going on with just beans. They had another study going on with a heavy berry diet. Anyway, you have all of these programs. But again, the idea is that you are
It's not just the place, but you also there's policies in place to help you. This is why, again, when you have the lunch break… lunch, there's a reason why there is a lunch break. That is for you to
kind of unwind, eat mindfully, take a little walk after that if you have to, all of that, right? So there is a program in place, and this is why I think I like well the lead from a building standpoint, and I like well to kind of complement it
To see, like, yes, do you have the spaces and do you have the material? All of those things you're thinking about, but you're kind of flipping that and saying, hey, do you have
the right filtration system. A, do you have clean water? Do you have
A space where you can eat painfully, and do you have a policy in place that gives people the time that they need
Righting. Again, same thing with the lighting. Do you have
smart lighting system
that can kind of help you. We actually did an interesting study, Christian, because again, Dr. Ebe was there. So and actually students in my research methods, undergraduate class, they're going to do a research study again
Because we have lighting systems where we can manipulate the lighting. And so we put participants in and we have them do like a writing task, reading task, and we have them take a quiz and then see if
the different lighting systems, like we compile like four different lighting systems to see if that has an effect on the outcome.
Right. I think even from a retail store standpoint, when we think about lighting is we did another study. We had different wine bottles under different lighting conditions, and we wanted to see if
the intent to purchase was different under the different lighting conditions
And it was a very interesting study. Anyways, that's on the side. But making sure that you have the right lighting for the participants to be productive
And stuff. Fitness, again, like you said, there's the formal spaces and the informal spaces. Like we said, our lounge area where students sit, can that become a yoga place? We also have these amazing staircase
That you can take from the first floor to the fourth floor, I mean, to the third floor, and then go to the fourth floor
And then you also have different little staircases and everything that you can use. If there are, again, a Colvin Center, because we have a swimming area, you have your racquetball areas, all sorts of you have your weightlifting areas
Massive space where… and you have indoor walking track. Sometimes it's too hot outside. So you have an indoor walking track where you can walk inside. So all of those considering
Mindfully, being very intentional to see and not just, again, going back to again, when you have the space to provide, but then do you also have the programs to support that?
Right? And yes, we do, because we have the dance class, so you have the spin class, the swimming class. So you have all of these. And then from the fitness standpoint, you also have the intramural little competitions among students. They say… I mean, competition is fun, who doesn't like to compete?
So there's an emphasis for that. Comfort. Again, there's a bigger emphasis, right? 10 points there.
Excellent. But again, this is your perceived comfort. So you're doing surveys, you're gathering feedback. And I know the university, they try to do, but like I said, it's important that you do for me to you do the feedback early on
As opposed to waiting till the end of a semester or end of a year, and you do periodic interviews throughout. And then and then you also do pre-post studies right where you
Look at the perceived comfort level and but comfort is from so many standpoints, right? Are we talking the chair comfort? Are we talking eye strain from a monitor? Are we talking
Thermal comfort. There are so many layers to comfort. So
Whatever the comfort is, I mean, holistically, right, looking at all aspects of it, because your eyes, I mean, your body, I mean, any, anything your
And then also kind of, I think it's also
When… do we have… do we have little spaces where you can kind of unwind? Ideally, like, if you have a pond, right? You're sitting down, you have a pod
You can kind of use that to really unwind and you want some time to yourself, right?
Is there spaces? Sometimes it is simple as having a different seating arrangement.
We have what we call centripetal and centrifugal sitting arrangements. So one is where the seating where you're facing each other
Right? So you're being very intentional about your social interaction, which is important for mental health also, right? But sometimes you go the other way. The chairs are facing away from each other because you want some quiet time
Just by yourself. So you're being very intentional in how you set
sitting in our lounges, in our… we have a great hall over there. Are we being very intentional in how we arrange the seating
So that we are taking into account comfort and mental health and all of that for for our so little things like that. And I think that's why I think I think well gives you this opportunity to
Try to come up with all these design interventions again to improve the health and well-being. Mind again, like you
Lane fur
Are you mindful, or is your mind full
Right. How do you go from where you say your mind is always full and occupied to being kind of more mindful? But that kind of translates across, right? You're looking at mental health
But I think that everything is connected, right? Because air quality could be related to your mental health and how you feel
Same thing with the water. If you have good water, if you have the good food that's related. If you have good lighting, that's related. If you have good fitness spaces and policies in place
few spaces that are perceived as comfortable
Right, so you see, it is it is
In a way, it's a holistic approach because you're looking at, I mean, when you look especially at and if well is focused on the well-being, physical well-being, mental well-being
And the social well-being
Right? For social well-being, are you providing
Spaces where people can face each other and talk. Or are you just providing spaces where individuals can just isolate. But then also in terms of curriculum, in terms of a program, are you providing opportunities
for individuals to interact and kind of grow and learn and stuff
All right
So again, for the future of Wales, we're thinking about reporting. There is obviously a growing demand for healthy workspaces. There will continue to be a growing demand. So are we doing everything in our power to kind of try
And if you want to integrate, well, you can think about it doesn't have to be costly interventions. What are little things that you can do
Right? To introduce design interventions in your space to kind of improve the health and well-being of people who might use the space. AI driven building management systems. Well, there's an
newer version, focusing on equity, resilience, occupant responses. Again, so the emphasis is health and well-being. You're looking at preconditions and then the optimizations, 40% again for the gold, or do you want to go for the 80%
Looking at air water nourishment, light fitness comfort in the mind.
different certification levels
Right?
So I'll leave it there. There's about five minutes. Does anybody want to share like about
What… if you were to kind of learn something from this well or from Lee, what are some changes that you might incorporate into your space to improve your health and wellbeing
Mm-hmm.
What are little things that you might do? What are some challenges that you're facing currently? And what might you do to improve your health and well-being in any space that you spend time in?
Well, I think for me it's primarily acoustics. Like, a lot of the…
Okay.
spaces I'm in, they have really bad echo, and…
That's all the… it would be nice to have a little bit of dampening in there.
Absolutely
And the rest is pretty good. So complaining at a high level.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah, yeah, no, no, and that's underrated, right? I mean, anybody didn't hear from any of the students, everybody's very quiet today.
I don't know, is it a rainy day where you're at, or I don't know.
You can also write in the chat window, you don't have to talk. So I was a little bit intimidating to talk to sort of an empty room.
Yeah. Yeah, yeah, yeah, feel free to just type it in the chat if you don't want to talk out loud
Yes.
Please, please.
I have an example I would like to share where I feel like the social aspect of especially
like, living quality at the company is huge. I know of a company who is… it's very progressive, they have very good furniture, they
Really try to consider their employees' health
So far that they are willing to pay for fitness
Nice.
Lessons for their employees as long as the employees go at least, I think 50 times per year. So that's like once a week because they say regularity
True.
Makes increases the benefit than if you just go once in a while it's not the same. So they want you to go a lot and then they will pay for it.
And it's really interesting because very few people, very few of the employees actually use this
Service
Because of the social anxiety of that they feel like, oh, I don't want to mix my work life and my private life too much, or that there is, like, stigmas associated with
Especially moving in a group and stuff like that, so I thought it was really interesting that even though companies provide these kind of services, sometimes it's hard for people to
want to use them because of their own like
I don't know, like their social standing or that they feel like, oh, I've spent eight hours already with these people, I don't want to spend even more time with them. We are, in fact, not family, we're just working together
True, true.
So it's… I think it's a… I think this company in particular does very well
But I thought it was interesting how so many more factors come into play
if people actually use it or not
Yeah, yeah, I think maybe I'm just thinking out loud. Thank you very much for sharing that.
I think maybe if there's an opportunity, you know, we're going to
actually have this health service as part of your workday. We are giving you one
2 days a week
where you can
leave early and use this. I don't know. You provide an incentive. But when we look at it as is it too
hours of the workday that they're losing, but maybe
the productivity gain might be much higher
from these two hours that they lost. Anyway, so thank you, thank you again. Anything else, anybody?
Yeah, General, go ahead, please.
This is for your presentation and the lecture today. While I was listening to your
And I was really trying to connecting
my experience, especially in Mongolia in terms of the indoor air quality, because I experienced really bad, serious
time in, back in Mongolia, especially the wintertime, and then I just this is just my self-reflection
And I
I think it's really hard to transform
quickly to move to the new
technology like for example the Mongolia, they want to they are trying to scale up electronic heating system to avoid indoor air quality. I mean
the bad air quality, because most of the people still, they use fuel. I mean, the coal
Yes, yes.
Yeah, and especially those living in the traditional house called GER, sorry, this is very hard to pronounce
So and then for me, when I was when I was working in Mongolia
four years ago when I saw that technology for me, it looked really simple and I was like, is it I can call this I mean, I can call this technology even because back in Korea or somewhere, perhaps like developed
so-called developed country, we don't use those
Simple technology, but they are starting using it. And then I realized that it's very difficult and hard for the people to make
The system
use in their real life, and then that's the reason
We are
I mean, that's one of the reasons I work in developing at international development field. And I just wanted to share it's
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Challenging, yeah, of course, and it's good technology, but it's very challenging in the real life.
Thank you. Thank you, thank you. Yes, yes, I think it's important to kind of shed light on air quality and if you can address, maybe suggest some suggestions. I know it's 10:32, sorry, sorry, I'm two minutes over. I see a quote by Rika. And so yeah, it's good to
Different, but maybe a four day week, but if you're getting more output, then why not? And then also, yeah, Mihira, thank you very much. And I just wanted to also kind of wish all of you a wonderful summer school and those of you who are there in person or you're watching online and
I also want to thank Michael, Michaela, Christian
Everybody just for providing me this opportunity. So hope everybody has an awesome rest of the summer or fall and day and winter and
Yeah, stay healthy, stay happy.
Thanks much, Olitia.
Let's see what I did tomorrow.
Thank you. Okay, bye.
All right, bye